Taking personal
responsibility for our health
is one of the most
important things we can do.
Regular exercise, not smoking, and
eating a healthy diet can
help prevent and even reverse
some of our most common diseases.
And most people know this… so
why don’t they eat healthier?
Watch the video to find out.
"Why Don't People Eat Healthier?"
Yes, media messages surrounding
nutrition are often
inconsistent and confusing,
but many Americans know
what constitutes a healthy diet.
I mean, does anyone
really think drinking brown
carbonated sugar water
is good for them?
At issue is that they don’t appear to be
translating their knowledge into action.
There are a number of reasons
people have such difficulty
changing their dietary behaviors.
While ignorance and
confusion may play a part,
the motivation to change is
likely much more important.
Certainly, we are living in
a world that pushes us to eat
whatever we want, regardless of
the long-term consequences.
But one of the major problems in
getting people to change their
behavior is the need to get them
to recognize the need to change.
For example, if you ask
people how much meat they eat,
or how much greasy food, eggs,
sweets, alcohol, butter,
they claim to be eating less
than the average person.
So, if people think they’re
at less risk than others,
they may dismiss advice
to eat more healthfully,
thinking that they already eat
healthier. Maybe they are?
No, people rated their own
eating behavior as healthier
on average even when their actual
eating habits were terrible.
For this reason, maybe health-
promotion campaigns need to make
people aware of how
badly they are eating.
But when you do that,
a strange thing happens.
If you challenge people with
the reality of what the average
person actually eats, they
change their answer to make
themselves appear as though they’re
still healthier than average.
When people's favorable
comparisons on risky behaviors
are threatened, they not
only reduce their estimates
of how often they engage
in those behaviors—
"oh, I don’t eat that much meat”—
but they also attenuate the
significance of those behaviors.
“Meat’s not that bad for you anyway.”
It’s the same personal fable
that smokers tell themselves.
Studies show that smokers
have a strong tendency
to underestimate all
smoking-related risks,
developing a series of
illusions and false beliefs
to support their choice
to keep on smoking.
Why do so many people continue
to light up in spite of
smoking’s harmful
effects to their health?
For many of the same reasons people
continue to eat unhealthy food.
First, they convince
themselves that they are less
at risk than others who
engage in the same behavior.
And in addition to this optimism
bias, smokers underestimate
the extent to which smoking
elevates lung cancer risk,
thinking two-pack-a-day smokers
only have like five times the risk
of getting lung cancer, when their
actual risk is 20-fold higher.
And anyway, many
smokers believe lung cancer
is mainly determined by one’s genes.
Many food-related hazards
share this same optimistic bias,
such as heart attacks and
heart disease (our #1 killer),
obesity, diabetes, and all the rest.
People are often quite
ingenious in finding reasons for
believing that their own risk is less
than the risk faced by their peers.
So, maybe public health advocates
need to be just as ingenious
in understanding the origins
of this unrealistic optimism
and in finding approaches
that help people gain a more
accurate picture of
their own vulnerability.
All sorts of work is being done
trying to reduce or eliminate
this bias, “but we must
consider the possibility that
reductions in optimistic
bias may lead to reductions
in self-esteem and
psychological well-being,”
if people start to realize
just how much risk they
truly face and how much they
have themselves to blame.
This reminds me of the tightrope
wire health professionals
have to walk, telling
people how much power
we all have over getting cancer.
This is the oft-cited paper
that calculated that we may
be able to prevent approximately
90 percent of human cancers.
(But by “present trends,” the
researcher was talking about
present trends of the 1960s
when the paper was published.)
They remain true to this day, though,
about a half century later.
Genetic factors are not the
major causes of chronic diseases.
Using identical twins to see
how much was really just
in your genes, of all the chronic
diseases they looked at,
cancers had the lowest
genetic component,
again only about 10 percent
attributable to bad genes.
What runs in families is bad habits.
But when you go out there and
tell everyone the good news
about how much power we
have over not getting cancer,
what about the people who already have it?
When people are diagnosed
with cancer, they often ask,
“Why me? Did I do something
wrong? Is this my fault?”
So you can imagine how the
message of, “well yeah, kinda,”
could be destructive for
patients or survivors.
In other words, a message that
is intended to empower people in
a prevention context could just
make cancer victims feel guilty.
But the truth is still the truth,
no matter how difficult it may be.
So, what we have to do is
try to guide patients to switch
from feelings of guilt to a
“responsibility” approach.
They have personal control;
they can make different
choices from then on.
We need to give them a sense
of agency in their life.
Better, though, to try to take
those steps before you get cancer.